Alright, today's דף Daf is דף ח. Daf Ches. We are continuing
in the,
actually we've moved on from the discussion of נידוי Niduy within the
part of the משנה Mishna where it speaks about מודרני ממך Midrani
mimcha
and
מנודני ממך. Menudani mimcha. Let me double check what was the language.
It's gotten into discussion about נידוי Niduy and חרם, Cherem, and on
the one hand there are definitely similarities to that within a נדר
Neder and גמרא Gemara used the phrase about to do התרה Hatara
to annul חרם Cherem and on the other hand it's not actually
a נדר Neder and whether somebody tries to use that term
whether that actually would be לשון נדר Lashon neder which is רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's position but the גמרא Gemara says but we do
not פוסקן Pasken that way. And now because in that discussion although
later we're going to get to a discussion about certain circumstances in
which we do a נידוי Niduy and not necessarily a classic נידוי
Niduy of a very severe violation but as a form of censure
that can sort of be released right away, and in that discussion
of course the focus was on somebody that loosely uses God's name
לבטלה. Levatala. Certainly what we saw in that discussion was sort of
the power of speech and that's of course so much central to
what this מסכת Masechet is about. So somebody just, you know, speaks
God's name loosely and therefore they're put in חרם Cherem which is
also through the power of speech and then that חרם Cherem is
released through another act of speech so there's obviously a lot there
that speaks to the major themes of the מסכת. Masechet. Okay so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
and now but in that discussion quoted אמר גידל אמר רב Amar
Giddel Amar Rav about a תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham מנדה את עצמו
Menadey et atzmo like putting himself
in חרם Cherem or if he puts himself in חרם Cherem he
can release himself from it.
And now the גמרא Gemara has another statement of אמר גידל אמר
רב Amar Giddel Amar Rav which is very directly relevant to the
concerns of מסכת נדרים. Masechet Nedarim. So let's take a look. ואמר
גידל אמר רב V'amar Giddel Amar Rav says Giddel in the name
of Rav top of דף ח Daf Ches עמוד א. Amud Aleph.
מניין שנשבעין לקיים את המצווה? M'nayin she'nishba'im l'kayem et hamitzvah?
How do you know you can take an oath, not a נדר,
Neder, an oath, a שבועה Shevuah to fulfill a מצווה? Mitzvah? שנאמר
נשבעתי ואקיימה, Shenemar nishbati v'akayemena, I've taken an oath and I will
fulfill, לשמור משפטי צדקך, Lishmor mishpatei tzidkecha, to observe your righteous edicts.
So therefore look it works. Now the גמרא Gemara assumes what it
means is either means like it's a good thing to do. It's
not a concern of שם שמיים Shem shamayim לבטלה Levatala because, you
know, the concern that we should have just off
with in the previous דף Daf that that would be good in
order to sort of give yourself, you know, impetus to encourage yourself
to go ahead and do it. Or you could also mean that
it is a, that it's binding as a שבועה. Shevuah. And the
גמרא Gemara really focuses on that second possibility. Why would it be
binding? והלא מושבע ועומד מהר סיני? V'lo mushba v'omed m'Har Sinai? He
already is foresworn from הר סיני Har Sinai to observe the commandments
and a שבועה Shevuah that is coming either to be מבטל מצווה,
Mivatel mitzvah, something to say I won't sit in a סוכה, Sukkah,
so that שבועה Shevuah is not binding because he's already pre-foresworn.
Or if somebody takes a שבועה Shevuah I will sit in a
סוכה Sukkah and then let's say he doesn't he has not transgressed
violating the שבועה Shevuah because that שבועה Shevuah doesn't take effect because
he already is obligated and אין שבועה חלה על שבועה. Ein shevuah
chal al shevuah. So how could such a שבועה Shevuah like this
be binding? So the גמרא Gemara says לא, Lo, wait it's not
הא קמשמע לן. Ha kamashma lan. No technically it's not binding but
it's teaching
us לזרוזון L'zeruzon משום לזרוזי נפשיה M'shum l'ziruzei nafshei that you can
do it even though it's not binding because it's a powerful way
of you to sort of encourage yourself, you know, in order to
do what you're supposed to do anyway. Like we know that in
life when we have obligations it doesn't necessarily mean we do it.
Sometimes we have to figure out like little tricks to get us
to do the things we're supposed to do or to pay attention
to them as well. Also remember when I was in high school
I read an essay about this which wound up, it wasn't called
laziness but it winds up being the way I operate a lot.
The way you get yourself to do something is you find something
else on your to-do list that you'd rather do less and then
in order to avoid the thing that the other thing you don't
want to do you make yourself do the thing anyway. Okay, so
anyway so you're allowed to do that. Now there is a little
bit of a question. The ר"ן Ran thinks that maybe actually it
is חל Chal except that you don't bring a קרבן Korban for
it. That the idea of something that's מושבע ועומד Mushba v'omed that
the second שבועה Shevuah isn't חל Chal might not mean that it's
not חל Chal altogether. So if you look at the ר"ן Ran
it
says as
the ר"ן Ran questions this and says. And
the Ran, והכי תימא הני מילי *ve'hachi teima hani milei*, it's about
ten lines down from the line הקרבן *hakorban*, maybe only this idea
that אין שבועה חלה על שבועה shvua chala al shvua, *ein shvuah
chala al shvuah* means you don't pay the קרבן korban, *korban* for
that שבועה shvuah *shvuah*, דהא לא מיחייב קרבן korban, *de'ha lo mechayev
korban*, but by בל יחל איכא *aval bal yachel ika*, maybe it's
still transgressing the prohibition of violating the שבועה shvuah, *shvuah*, אפילו בדבר
מצוה mitzvah *afilu bedvar mitzvah*. No, והכי תימא נשבע לבטל את המצוה
*ve'hachi teima nishba levatel es hamitzvah*, הכא נמי לומר *hacha nami lomar*,
דביה מאי מצוה mitzvah *d'bei mai mitzvah*? מקרבן לא מיחייב *mikarban lo
mechayev*, it should have said that maybe there's no קרבן korban, *korban*
but there is בל יחל *bal yachel*. Okay, and then he goes
on, so he says, אלא הכי קא משמע לן *ela hachi ka
mashma lan*, so basically says, ומדלג על הגמרא *umidaleg al hagemara*, I'm
getting too much, כי דחזינן בדוכתא אחרינא דמדמי שבועה shvuah לנדר *ki
dachazinan beduchta achrina demidamei shvuah leneder* and then ומאי קרבן אלא לאו
ומאי מלקות ולאו הכי סריכא *u'mai korban ela lav u'mai malkos velav
hachi sricha*. So ומאי קא משמע לן נשבע לבטל את המצוה *u'mai
ka mashma lan nishba levatel es hamitzvah*? אלא הכי קא משמע לן
דשרי ליה לזרוזי נפשיה *ela hachi ka mashma lan deshrei lei lezaruzei
nafshei*. So now about eight lines before the lines get wide: ודאי
לא איצטריך האי קרא למימר דשבועה חלה לגבי בל יחל *vaday lo
itztareich hai kra lemeimar deshvuah chala legabei bal yachel*, because of course
it is חל chal. *chal* for בל יחל *bal yachel*, meaning the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says this is taken for granted that even though
אין שבועה חלה על שבועה shvua chala al shvua, *ein shvuah chala
al shvuah*, that's only for קרבן *korban*, but for בל יחל *bal
yachel* it does take effect. דהא לא צריך למימר *de'ha lo tzarich
lemeimar*, that's obvious that a שבועה shvua *shvuah* can be חל chal?
*chal* על שבועה shvua *al shvuah* for בל יחל *bal yachel*. אלא
הכי קאמר מן השבועה הוא דהוי ליה לזרוזי נפשיה *ela hachi ka'amar
min hashvuah hu dehavay lei lezaruzei nafshei* and since שבועה shvua *shvuah*
מן השמיים השביעוהו בכך *min hashamayim hishbi'uhu bekach*, so ומאי נפקא מינה
*u'mai nafk'a minah*. So the ר״ן *Ran* says that actually this principle
אין שבועה shvua, חלה על שבועה shvua *ein shvuah chala al shvuah*
just means you don't pay the קרבן *korban*, but you'd still be
transgressing the לאו *lav* of בל יחל *bal yachel* and you would
be subject to getting מלקות *malkos*. Now that's not the simple sense
of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, and if you look at the שפתי
אברהם *Sifsei Avraham* here on הש״ס *ha'shas* at the very bottom, he
says דהא מושבע ועומד mushba v'omed *de'ha mushba ve'omed*,
he says, and look at the רמב״ן *Ramban* על התורה *al haTorah*,
פרשת חוקת *parshas Chukas*, so look at the רמב״ן *Ramban*
על הש״ס *al ha'shas*, very bottom of the דף daf. *daf*, okay,
קובץ רמב״ן פרשת חוקת *kovetz Ramban parshas Chukas*, שכתב אפילו בקיום מצות
עשה אין חלות *shekasav afilu bekiyum mitzvas asei ein chalus*, שאי נשבע
לקיים את המצוה וביטלן אין מתחייב בשום שבועה shvua לא קרבן ולא
מלקות *she'im nishba lekayem es hamitzvah u'bitlan ein mischayev beshum shvuah lo
korban velo malkos*. So the רמב״ן *Ramban* says as against that רמב״ן
*Ramban* that אין שבועה shvua. חלה על שבועה shvua? *ein shvuah chala
al shvuah* or a שבועה shvua *shvuah* to do a מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah*, not only is there no קרבן *korban*, there's no מלקות *malkos*,
it's not חל chal. *chal* at all. And the point of רב
גידל אמר רב *Rav Giddel amar Rav* is to tell you that
even though it's not חל chal *chal*, it's a good thing to
do to encourage yourself to do a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*, maybe I
don't know, somehow it's חל chal *chal* in some metaphysical sense but
not in any, yes, exactly, not in any actual practical הלכתית halachically
*halachic* sense.
But the ר״ן *Ran* actually goes so far to say it's חל
*chal* even for a לאו *lav*, and the חידוש *chidush* of רב
גידל אמר רב *Rav Giddel amar Rav* is not to tell you
that it's חל *chal*, but to tell you it's actually a good
thing to do this as a way of encouraging yourself to fulfill
your obligation. So that's one statement. That's about שבועה shvua *shvuah*. But
now we get to another very relevant statement that actually brings in
the whole נדר neder *neder* idea. So let's take a look. ואמר
רב גידל אמר רב האומר אשנה פרק זה ashneh perek zeh. *ve'amar
Rav Giddel amar Rav ha'omer eshne perek zeh*, somebody says I'll study
this פרק perek. *perek* today, או אשנה מסכת masechet זו *o eshne
masechet zu*, or I'm studying
this מסכת masechta. *masechet*, נדר גדול נדר neder gadol nadar. לאלקי ישראל
*neder gadol nadar l'Elokei Yisrael*. He has made a high vow, so
thank you, that's what I'm talking about. So he has made a
big vow to the God of Israel. So first of all, you
didn't say לשון נדר lashon neder, *lashon neder*, you didn't say לשון
שבועה lashon shvuah, *lashon shvuah*, you just said I'm going to do
this. Okay, so number one, that's a question, since when does that
create in some sense of a שבועה shvua *shvuah* or a נדר
neder. *neder*? Okay, besides the problem of אין שבועה shvua, חלה על
שבועה shvua. *ein shvuah chala al shvuah* whatever. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to say, so let's take a look. So the
גמרא gemara, *Gemara* says, והלא מושבע ועומד mushba v'omed, הוא *ve'halo mushba
ve'omed hu*, so the גמרא gemara *Gemara* treats this as a שבועה
shvua *shvuah*, האומר אשנה *ha'omer eshne*, to do something is a לשון
lashon שבועה shvua. *lashon shvuah*, right, not לשון נדר lashon neder. *lashon
neder*. So aren't you מושבע ועומד mushba v'omed *mushba ve'omed*? So that's
the same thing as we asked before. How does it take effect?
Okay, and you can't say it's מצוה mitzvah, לזרזי אינשי *mitzvah lezarzei
inshi* because that was the thing in 79, in 79 שמעת מיניה
*shamas minah* that it's a good thing to do it. Here it
says if you do this it's, you know, it's חל *chal*, it's
a נדר neder. *neder* or a שבועה shvua. *shvuah*, we'll talk about
that in a minute. So what do you mean it's חל *chal*?
והלא מושבע ועומד mushba v’omed. הוא *ve'halo mushba ve'omed hu*? ואין שבועה
shvua, חלה על שבועה shvua? *ve'ein shvuah chala al shvuah*. When should
that take effect on another? So the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* says, no,
מאי קא משמע לן דאפילו זירוזי דעלמא *mai ka mashma lan d'afilu
ziruzei d'alma*. So maybe it's telling you okay, but it's חל *chal*
enough for, thank you, you're able to do it to encourage yourself.
Or it's חל *chal* enough, meaning maybe there's some metaphysical idea that
it takes effect even if הלכתית *halachically* you wouldn't transgress. And that
helps you encourage yourself. If that's what he's saying, היינו דרב גידל
קמייתא *hainu de'Rav Giddel kammaisa*, that's the first statement of רב גידל
*Rav Giddel*. So the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* says no, הכא קא משמע
לן דאי בעי פטר נפשיה *hacha ka mashma lan d'ei bei patar
nafshei*, like Michael says, since you could exempt yourself by קריאת שמע
שחרית וערבית krias shema shacharis v'arvis. *Krias Shema shacharis ve'arvis*, you could
learn something else today, you don't have to learn this פרק perek,
*perek*. Actually the very basic minimum of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah, *Talmud
Torah* is saying שמע Shema *Shema* morning and evening, right, it says
ושננתם לבניך *v'shinantam l'vanecha*. לבניך ודברת בם.
The פשט pshat of those פסוק pasuk is not about קריאת שמע,
Krias Shema, the פשט pshat of that פסוק pasuk is about תלמוד
תורה, Talmud Torah. and it says ובשכבך ובקומך, v'shachbacha uv'kumecha,
so the explicit mandate of the תורה, Torah, learning תורה Torah is
when you go to sleep and get up, when you go to
sleep by saying קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, but it's not like some
bizarre saying, "Oh, well you happen to be saying קריאת שמע, Krias
Shema, that happens to be something where you discharge תלמוד תורה." Talmud
Torah, The point is, it's a deeper one, that the פשט pshat
of the פסוקים psukim that we learn from the הלכה halacha of
saying שמע Shema, is actually פסוקים psukim about תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah.
which is why there are serious positions in the תנאים Tannaim that
קריאת שמע Krias Shema is not דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, but it's מדרבנן, m'Derabanan,
because even though you've got פסוקים, psukim, those פסוקים psukim in the
פשט pshat are not talking about שמע, Shema, they're פסוקים psukim in
the פשט pshat talking about תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. So the גמרא
gemara says that's why also the ברכות brachos of קריאת שמע Krias
Shema you discharge the ברכות תורה. brachos Torah. So when the גמרא
gemara says you discharge, it doesn't mean "Oh, by chance you happened
to have said some פסוקים." psukim. You don't discharge because you say
פסוקים psukim in פסוקי דזמרא. Pesukei d'Zimrah. The idea is that specifically
קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, the פסוקים psukim that we say, we're saying
that as a fulfillment of ובשכבך ובקומך v'shachbacha uv'kumecha which at the
פשט pshat level is the מצוה mitzvah of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah.
So therefore when you're doing the פסוקים psukim of שמע, Shema. you're
doing the מצוה mitzvah, of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah
And therefore that's the bare minimum. Anything else you don't technically have
to do, or you know, I mean obviously there's a חיוב chiyuv
and there's, you know, you should strive to learn תורה Torah as
much as possible, but you don't have to and certainly you don't
have to learn particularly this פרק. perek So therefore it's not מושבע
ועומד mushba v’omed, if he misses to do in this particular form.
And therefore it does take effect. Okay? So
משום הכי חלה שבועה עליה. mishum hachi chala shvuah aleiya. Since you
could, you don't have to learn specifically this פרק, perek A, you
don't have to learn the whole day technically, right? I mean you
should, but I'm saying as a bare minimum you can discharge with
just שמע. Shema So therefore there's nothing to sort of obligating you
to learn the particular פרק perek. or the particular מסכת masechta, that
you're obligating yourself for, so you're not מושבע ועומד, mushba v'omed because
there's nothing obligating you to do this particular thing. So therefore your
שבועה shvua, takes effect. Yes. But the
thing is, is שמע Shema is not תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah per
se, it's קבלת עול מלכות שמים. Kabbalas Ol Malchus Shamayim. It's seeing
it as learning תורה Torah per se. That's true, so when we
get to מסכת ברכות Masechet Brachos we'll discuss that, the way חז"ל
Chazal understand it and the way it exists in the דאבנינג davening
it exists as a separate מצוה mitzvah of קריאת שמע. Krias Shema.
But ultimately it's always, it retains its original anchor in the פסוקים
psukim as a form of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah. as well, which
is also why the פסוקים psukim of the ברכות brachos of קריאת
שמע Krias Shema also functions as ברכות תלמוד
תורה.
brachos
Talmud Torah.
Yes. But it's for this particular מצוה, mitzvah, it's not just any
מצוה, mitzvah and it's not like the kind of מצוה mitzvah, that
I'm חייב chayav on. No, first of all, no, first of all,
first of all, you know, if you're already חייב chayav that particular
מצוה, mitzvah, then you'd be מושבע ועומד mushba ve'omed if you say
it, but let's say you said to do it in a form
that you wouldn't be exactly חייב. chayav. Let's say you said I'm
going to give a hundred dollars, you know, to בית אי"ר, Beis
AYR, right? So you know, I'm going to give a hundred dollars
to this particular צדקה, tzedakah, right?
So even though you're חייב chayav for this צדקה, tzedakah, you're not
חייב chayav to give that amount to this particular place. So then
it might actually be חל. Now the question is how much is
it חל? You didn't say לשון שבועה, shvua, you just said I'm
going to do it. And anyway it says נדר neder? and then
it calls it a mandate and then it says it's a שבועה,
shvua. so what exactly is going on? So let's unpack this. So
first of all, there's a ר"ן, Ran, my first point which I
should say, which is not פשט pshat of the גמרא. gemara But
the ר"ן Ran does not like the פשט pshat of this גמרא
Gemara that you're not חייב chayav to learn תורה Torah all day.
So the ר"ן Ran says, if you look about six, five lines
down the wide lines, הכא משמע משום דכיון דבדיבורא בעלמא מיפטר נפשו,
hacha mashma mishum dekeivan devidibura be’alma mifatar nafsho, he says, he says
הכי קאמר משום דכיון דבחד פסוקא פטר נפשו. hacha ka amar mishum
dekeivan dev’chad pasuka patar nafsho. He says, משתמע mishtameia it's not דוקא
davka when you're exempt by saying it even in the morning in
שמע Shema in the morning and שמע in the evening. שהרי כל
אדם חייב ללמוד תמיד. sheharei kol adam chayav lilmod tamid. You have
to learn every single minute! יומם ולילה! yomam valaila! כפי כוחו. k’fi
kocho. But since, you know, I mean if you've got to go
to work or whatever, right, exactly. But as
as to the maximum of your ability, you have to use every
spare minute to learn תורה. Torah. כדאמרינן בפרק דמנחות, k’damrinan b’perek d’Menachos,
לא ניתנו דברי תורה אלא לאוכלי המן, lo nitnu divrei Torah ella
l’ochlei haman, שנאמר והגית בו יומם ולילה. she’ne’emar v’hagita bo yomam valaila.
Now the פשט pshat is תורה Torah has to be sharp in
your mouth, doesn't mean you have to learn every minute. But anyway,
וקריאת שמע שחרית וערבית סגי להכי. ukrias Shema shacharis v’arvis sagi l’hachi.
Anyway, so we could have a whole שיעור shiur about what is
the extent of the מצוה mitzvah. of תלמוד תורה. talmud torah, Anyway,
but let's just see how he answers it coming from his perspective
that you are חייב chayav to learn every minute, at least every
minute that you have that you're not חייב, chayav, you're not responsible
to do other things. אלא מיהו קאמר דכיון דסגי להכי, ella mihu
ka’amar dekeivan desagi l’hachi, אלא מיהו קאמר דהיכא דמשתבע לקיים מצוה שאינה
מפורשת בהדיא, ella mihu ka’amar dehacha d’mishtava l’kayeim mitzvah she’eina meforeshes b’hedya,
שבועה חלה עליה. shvuah chala aleiya.
So the way the ר"ן Ran solves it is by quoting another
one of his positions, which is we say אין שבועה חלה על
השבועה ein shvuah chala al hashvuah or you're מושבע ועומד. It only
applies to things that are explicit in the תורה. Torah. But things
that you're obligated to do in the תורה Torah that are not
explicit, we don't say you're מושבע ועומד, because it's not black and
white, and a שבועה shvua would be חל. So the way the
ר"ן Ran reads it is, "Oh, of course you're חייב chayav to
learn תורה Torah every minute." Okay, but since it's not explicit in
the פסוקים... psukim... The only thing that's explicit in the פסוקים psukim
is like, you know, בשכבך ובקומך, b'shochbecha u'vkumecha, קריאת שמע שחרית וערבית.
krias shema shacharis v'arvis, Therefore the שבועה shvua will be חל on
any learning that goes beyond the obligation that's explicit in the פסוקים.
psukim. Okay?
Now by the way, the other answer we could have said is
you're חייב chayav to learn every minute, but it doesn't mean you
have to learn particularly this מסכת. I could learn every single day
and do חזרה chazara on מסכת בבא קמא, maseches Bava Kamma, and
I'll never get around to מסכת בבא מציעא, maseches Bava Metzia, right?
Now I'm יוצא ידי חובתי yotzei yedei chovati every single minute. Okay,
so the simplest sense, first of all, of this גמרא, Gemara just
from a perspective of people who want to give a שיעור, shiur,
this is a great שיעור shiur to give on שבועות Shavuos night
while we're waiting for it. But anybody who wants to give a
שיעור shiur on the extent of the מצוות תלמוד תורה, mitzvas talmud
torah, the פשט pshat of this גמרא Gemara is that the minimum
is קריאת שמע שחרית וערבית, krias shema shacharis v'arvis, and that's פשט
pshat of a number of גמרות. gemaras. But there are those that
want to say that you have a מצוה, mitzvah you know, יומם
ולילה, yomam valaylah, there's a מצוה mitzvah of, you know, every single
second. And therefore, the ones who use this, and then with the
גמרא, Gemara. you'll get A: you might not be obligated to learn
this particular מסכת, or B: it doesn't give the words of the
גמרא, Gemara or D: what the ר"ן Ran says is that it's
not explicit that you're חייב chayav to learn every minute. And since
it's not explicit, the only thing that's explicit is קריאת שמע שחרית
וערבית, for all other aspects of תלמוד תורה, Torah שבועה shvua is
חל on it. Okay, so that's some perspective of the מצוות תלמוד
תורה. mitzvas talmud torah. But let's go back to our prime discussion,
which is the idea of a שבועה shvua, and נדר. neder. So
we've got a double problem here. The double problem is the following:
number one is all he said was that you're going to do
something. You didn't say, "I'm taking a שבועה," shvua. "I'm taking a
נדר." neder, Okay? Now, it is treated as if, sometimes the גמרא
Gemara says, as if you like, you know, you do a דבר
טוב davar tov three times, that's as if you're מקבל נדר. mekabel
neder. Here you just said it once though, but maybe, you know,
it is saying, but like if you commit yourself to do a
sort of a serious type of a thing that's a דבר מצוה
davar mitzvah to some degree, that's a, that can, religious conviction, maybe
that does count somewhat. I mean, is it really הלכתית a שבועה
shvua or נדר? neder. Or is it just as if it, it
was? Now that's problem number one. Problem number two is that
the גמרא Gemara uses the language of מושבע ועומד because classic, that
is the right language for a שבועה shvua about doing something. But
the way he says it about an אמורא Amora is נדר גדול
נדר. neder gadol neder, Why does he use that language? Now, if
you combine those two, you'll actually realize that what we're really talking
about is the phenomenon in the תורה Torah of a נדר. neder.
וידור יעקב
נדר לאמר, vayidor Yaakov neder laymor, יהי אלקים עמדי y'hi Elokim imadi
etc., וכל אשר תתן לי עשר אעשרנו לך. v'chol asher titein li
aser asrnu lach. So Jacob didn't say, הריני מקבל עלי, hareini mekabel
alay, you know, בשבועה, beshvua, blah blah blah. He didn't say the
word שבועה. shvua He didn't say the word נדר, neder meaning the
תורה Torah described it. The verbs the תורה Torah. used to describe
it was וידור יעקב נדר לאמר. vayidor Yaakov neder laymor. But if
you look at the actual words that came out of Jacob's mouth,
they were just, "God, if you do this for me, I will
give you a מעשר." maaser. But he said it with a type
of a conviction of like he was accepting upon himself this as
a real obligation, and that's when you start binding of a נדר.
neder So that seems to be exactly this phenomenon. Meaning, if somebody
views himself, I mean you have to get to their mind, like,
what do you need to be thinking in your mind? You know,
do you need to, do you need to really accept it as
a real קבלה kabbalah etc., you know? But it doesn't need a
particular, like words, right? I mean, and we see actually that, you
know, if you look at what he said before about the יד,
yad, if you just says הרי עלי, harei alay, it's language of
נדר. neder, You know, you didn't use language of, you didn't use
language of קונם, konam, you just said הרי זה אסור עלי, harei
zeh asur alay, that could be a לשון נדר, neder right? All
you've said, you know, there's no magic words there, there's no unique,
you know, technical words of a נדר neder or קונם konam or
whatever, you just said it's forbidden to me. So if you said,
"I'm accepting upon myself," you know, "to do the דף יומי," daf
yomi, why should that not even be a לשון of קבלה? kabbalah?
Okay? And that's what you have in the תורה. Torah, The problem
is, is again that, is it a נדר neder or is it
a שבועה? shvua And it's not just a question of the fact
that the גמרא Gemara. calls it both, but it's also a question
of whether you can say "I'm מקבל mekabel on myself to do
this," because the idea of a שבועה shvua is different than the
idea of a קבלה. kabbalah. Meaning the idea of a שבועה shevuah
is, "I'm swearing in the name of God that I will do
this," right? So it's not like I accept, I create upon myself
a נדר, neder such a legal obligation, right? "I'm מקבל mekabel on
myself the obligation to do this." Is that right? A שבועה shevuah
is like I take an oath in the name of God and
if I'm, and I am lying or I won't fulfill it, I
will have violated my oath, right? That's not what a נדר neder
is. A נדר neder, isn't like a promise that I'm going to
violate. A נדר neder is I create an— If I say, "I'm,
you know, I'm committing to," you know, if או
אי o i says it's about a status, I make this object
forbidden, or if conceptually use the idea of נדר neder to obligate
myself, right? Think about the difference. How, in your mind, if I
said, some, somebody said, "I swear I'm going to do this," and
they didn't do it, right? So they have violated their oath, right?
That's how you think about it. They took a שבועה, they violated
the oath, they swore in the name of God, and then there's
a sense of desecrating the name of God because they used God
as their witness etc. Okay, that's if you said "I swear I'm
going to do this." It's very different if you say, "I'm... accepted
upon myself the obligation to do this, right? It's not like you
violated that oath that you made, it's like you're trying to create
a sense of obligation and then you're not living up to that
obligation that you had accepted upon yourself, right? So very similar, that
is similar to the idea of נדר neder, in the fact that
it's not about like a status of an object being forbidden, but
it's about creating like a type of a metaphysical reality; like I'm
constructing, I'm creating the sense that I'm now obligated to do this,
okay? And that's logically how we think, right? אני מקבל ani mekabel
on myself to do something, right? It's very different than when I
take an oath, right? I try to create this sense of obligation.
So that really is the biblical idea of נדר, neder right? Of
נדר מצוה. neder mitzva. It's similar in that it creates a metaphysical
status rather than it's like a verbal promise or verbal statement about
the past or the future which is שבועה. Creates a metaphysical status.
It's done without any magic words, right? הרי זו אסורה, Harei zu
asura, הרי עלי, Harei alai, שונה פרק זה, shoneh perek zeh,
something like that would be a לשון נדר. neder. Okay, and
but the question is how does it exist? Because until now we've
been learning נדר neder as just objects being forbidden, we haven't been
learning them as creating obligations upon yourself. So on the one hand,
it exactly fits the biblical idea of נדר מצוה neder mitzva and
you understand why נדב Nadav wants to call it a נדר neder
rather than a שבועה because conceptually it's about creating a sense of
obligation. Number one. Number two is you understand why it doesn't need
any special words, it doesn't have any special words in the Torah.
Maybe you have to say like, maybe it's not just saying like
I'm going to try to do without slow-mo, I'm committed to do
it, maybe you have to be a little bit more like I'm
accepting upon myself the obligation, right? Maybe there's a line between the
normal promises we make upon ourselves and doing something that's deep and
significant, right? It's like if you say that's it I'm not eating
any, any cake, right? It's cake אסור עלי, asur alai, so somewhere
this line crosses even if there aren't any magic words between just
trying to commit yourself to something as opposed to create a real
obligation. But nevertheless, we understand that phenomenon, we understand why it's similar
to the world of נדר, neder why it's נדר neder in the
Torah. We just don't know where you get this in terms of
all of מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim that until now don't know of
this idea. And the גמרא Gemara immediately uses language of שבועה. So
there's an interesting debate here between the ר"ן Ran and the רא"ש.
Rosh. So let's take a look at the ר"ן. Ran. The ר"ן
Ran says the following, he says, yeah,
1.4. So right as the last wide line, המפקיד אומר לשומר, hamifkid
omer lashomer, the first ר"ן, Ran, right? כלומר ואף אגב דקאמרת נדר
גדול, klomar ve'af agav dekammarta neder gadol, שבועה קאמרת. shvua kammarta. No,
it doesn't mean נדר. neder It means שבועה. דאמרי ביה בשבועה de'amri
bei bishvua אשנה פרק perek, זה. So the נדר neder, didn't catch
on the person, it caught on the study, אלא ואיידי דקאמרת כעין
דתנא בסיפא, ela ve'aydi dekammarta ke'ein detanna besifa, קאמר הכא נדר. ka'amar
hacha neder. Okay, it's not... כי נדרי רשעים נדר וכו'. ki nidrei
resha'im neder vechu'. So the ר"ן Ran basically
says the גמרא Gemara was לאו דוקא. lav davka. It really means,
and as we see in the later discussion, it discusses it as
שבועה חלה על שבועה, but the guy really made a שבועה, and
how come, how come the סיפא seifa didn't want to learn this
פרק how do I create a שבועה? Oh, so what also forgot
to say was that what you said was שבועה, I'm going to
learn this פרק. Okay, so two more pieces of information were missing
according to the ר"ן. Ran. Number one that the guy said the
language of שבועה, and number two that when the גמרא Gemara says
נדר neder? it means a שבועה. Obviously that is a hard read
of the גמרא. Gemara, Take a look at the רא"ש. Rosh. רא"ש
Rosh is...
does anybody read into the גמרא Gemara, and say it doesn't mean?
No, he says that's what the גמרא Gemara means. Okay, now take
a look at the רא"ש, Rosh, רש"י שפיר דכנדרי מצוה Rashi shapir
dechenidrei mitzva on the right hand margin. He says, נדר
neder גדול נדר, neder
the first wide line of the רא"ש. Rosh. ולאו היינו נדר ממש,
velav haynu neder mamash, ולאו היינו נדר lav haynu neder אלא שמתפיס
בדבר הנדור. ela shematpis bedavar hanadur.
Okay, then what is it? אלא מחשבינן ליה כאילו נדר לצדקה, ela
mechashvinan lei ke'ilu nadar litzdaka, דהיינו נדר בפיך זו צדקה. dehaynu neder
beficha zu tzedaka.
So he says no, he's trying to carve out that there is
something that is in the נדר neder category that actually does create
a personal obligation. Where do we find something like that? Not actually
about like I'm obligated myself to learn, but we find something like
that in terms of what he calls, in terms of I'm obligating
myself to give צדקה. tzedaka. We learned that before, right? That נדר
בפיך
זו צדקה. neder beficha zu tzedaka. So if you say I'm obligating
myself to do צדקה, tzedaka, that does become an obligation. So modeling
after that, we say you can obligate yourself to do other מצוות.
mitzvos. Now it sounds like it's a type of דרבנן. derabbanan. Okay,
we also have to ask where do you get this idea... But
like צדקה, tzedakah, let's see the next line. דלא מוסיף דחומרא הוא
דכתיב דאית ביה יומא דאורייתא. delo mosif dechumra hu dechtiv de'it bei
yoma d'raisa. ואף על גב דאמרינן לקמן פרק
אלו נדרים שנדר חל על דבר מצוה כדבר הרשות, v'af al gav
d'amrinan kamman perek eilu nedarim sheneder chal al devar mitzvah kidvar hareshus,
that a נדר neder, can take effect on a מצוה, mitzvah so
it's not a problem. A שבועה can't take effect, but a נדר
neder, can. Okay? היינו בנדר גמור שמתפיס בדבר אסור ואפילו הכי חייל
על דבר מצוה. hainu b'neder gamur shematfis bedavar assur v'afilu hachi chayal
al devar mitzvah. Okay,
I don't want to get into the details about that, but basically
it means if I take a שבועה I won't sit in the
סוכה, sukkah, it doesn't work because I'm basically going against my obligation
to
sit in the סוכה. sukkah. If I take a נדר, neder סוכה
sukkah is אסור עלי, assur alai,
then that is an indirect or not a direct countering. I'm just
making סוכה sukkah forbidden and then when it comes time to do
the מצוה, Mitzvah, then that's already forbidden. So okay, so anyway, so
point is, so why does the גמרא Gemara, have a problem, a
שבועה חלה על שבועה, since we're talking about נדר? neder נדר neder
doesn't go, can work even though there's a מצוה. So the ר"ן
Ran says, so the
ר"ן Ran says,
אבל בנדר כי האי, aval b'neder ki hai, no, that's a normal
נדר neder, which is like making objects forbidden, like a סוכה sukkah
forbidden. But a נדר neder like this, שדומה לצדקה, sh'domeh l'tzedakah, what
can be בו שחל על דבר מצוה? bo shechal al devar mitzvah?
Now this is like a צדקה tzedakah נדר, neder it's not your
classic נדר, neder and therefore maybe it won't take effect on top
of this existing מצוה obligation. וגמרינן משבועה דאינה חלה על דבר מצוה.
v'gamrinan mishvua d'einah chala al devar mitzvah. So it should be like
a שבועה because again if this is a נדר neder that creates
a personal obligation then it effectively is like a שבועה, right? So
you call it a נדר neder but it's effectively like a שבועה.
So if you can't have a שבועה to do something you're already
obligated, you can't have a נדר neder to do something you're already
obligated. Okay? וגמרינן משבועה דאינה חלה על דבר מצוה ואיצטריך למיסמך מידי
דשבועה דחמירא. v'gamrinan mishvua d'einah chala al devar mitzvah v'itztarich l'mismach midi
dishvua d'chamira. Okay, I don't want to go into that. So basically,
so what the ר"ן Ran actually does is the ר"ן Ran preserves
the sense of the גמרא. Gemara. Yes, it's a נדר, neder it's
a special type of a נדר neder which we'll call like like
נדרי צדקה, nidrei tzedakah, but actually create a personal sense of an
obligation and they follow the rules of a שבועה that just because
they're, they effectively are the same to obligate you to do something
and therefore can't take effect on something you're already obligated. But you
can take a נדר צדקה neder tzedakah because I don't have to
give to this particular cause or to that particular cause even though
there's a generic צדקה tzedakah obligation. So I can also have a
נדר neder. to learn a particular דף גמרא daf Gemara because I
don't have to learn this particular דף. daf So the ר"ן Ran
really says what I was saying except you know, except he says
where do we have this
הלכתא אמירתא hilchasa amirta of like צדקה? tzedakah? שקויח. shkayach. Since when
do we learn הלכה halacha something added in the תורה, Torah, you
know? So the ר"ן Ran asks where do we have a הלכה
halacha category that נדר neder can create a personal obligation, this idea
of נדרי מצוה, nidrei mitzvah, because we have it by צדקה. tzedakah.
Okay, now first of all, so this is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, דרבנן, d'rabbanan,
not clear. Maybe it's a דרבנן d'rabbanan type of an extension. It's
something that רב יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar Rav is the
only person to introduce this idea of נדרי מצוה, nidrei mitzvah, right?
Until we've never heard of it anywhere else in ש"ס Shas except
this one place. So you know, it seems like it's not a
דאורייתא d'oraisa category even though it's assumed that it's in the narratives
of the תורה, Torah number one. Number two is, so why does
it work by צדקה, tzedakah, right? Meaning doesn't this really just beg
the question, oh we have it by צדקה, tzedakah, but if נדר
neder is about objects, not about obligation, why does it work by
צדקה? tzedakah? And the answer might be, and the answer
in our סוגיא, sugya, maybe we can discuss this.
Yeah, I know there's a פסוק, pasuk, so but conceptually why does
it work? So it might work because in the end by צדקה,
tzedakah, it takes effect on your money, right? You can also make
a נדר צדקה, neder tzedakah,
you identify money as צדקה. tzedakah. If you take a נדר neder
to give צדקה, tzedakah, maybe that creates a type of a, the
רמב"ן Ramban says this, maybe it creates a type of a lien
on your money, a type of an obligation on your on your
property, although not a particular property, because again ten dollars when you
have a thousand dollars, which ten dollars? Okay. But anyway, maybe it
translates into an object. So if you then use, if
the נדר neder works by צדקה tzedakah because it is ultimately going
to be physically translate something from physical, and the אסור אשינה assur
ashina נדר neder also also translates physical, right? אסור אשינה? assur ashina?
So where, right? So anyway, so there you say it is possible
that that then becomes a model of creating a נדר neder to
create a מצוה responsibility or obligation upon yourself, at least in the
מצוה context.
Yes. Well the essential conceptual distinction that I made between שבועה and
נדר. neder Yes, שבועה obligates because you use God's name, yes, or
something of.
Right. Right.
Nothing of the
sort already obligates me נדר neder? and being thought of as צדקה.
tzedakah. Just my own language.
Yes, so that's correct, that is the primary difference and that's why
I said that accepting an obligation as a שבועה is because I've
violated like you know God's name. Here it's somehow the idea like
a קרבן, it's sort of like it's like a do-it-yourself Judaism, the
same way you know, you can go with... Of צדקה. tzedakah. Just
my own language. Yes, exactly. So that's correct, that is the primary
difference and why I said that, accepting an obligation as a שבועה
is because I violate God's name. Here it's somehow the idea like
a קרבן, it's sort of like it's a do it yourself Judaism.
The same way you can as חז"ל Chazal says if you make
a נדר neder it's like כאילו בנה במה. ke'ilu banah bamah. Like
the same way your words can create קדושה kedushah in a קרבן,
your words can make certain objects forbidden, and that's why they draw
on the idea of קרבנות, korbanot, קונם. konam. And the same way,
you know, the תורה Torah can put upon you obligations that come
from God, maybe your words can create obligations. So that's the חדוש
chiddush that your words can create these metaphysical obligations, but that is
the new realm that we're entering, right? Normally you have your שבועה
is a violation of your oath and a violation of, you know,
God's name, but it's not as much of an obligation as you're
violating the oath, whereas a נדר neder creates a change in status.
The idea of נדרי מצוה, nidrei mitzvah, actually your words create an
obligation, okay? And that is, you know, and that's like a different
type of an idea. But if I make a promise to you,
the obligation is I don't want to break my promise, right? But
can I just make a can I obligate myself and create an
through my words create that sense of obligation? I don't think an
oath always applies and promises to myself, right? So that's the issue
here. So again, just step back in the context because I'm spending
time on this because conceptually it's very
powerful simply because it ultimately gets back to what we have in
the תורה Torah, binding by all the נדרים nedarim in the תורה,
Torah ultimately religious promises to give something to God. Now, again, where
like I just mentioned at the first day, בחרמתי את אלוהיהם, becheramti
et eloheihem, וידר יעקב נדר, vayiidar Yaakov neder, right?
And ultimately that would translate into a type of this צדקה tzedakah
reality that something is given to God and it translates into an
object. But it seems from the פסוקים psukim that it's basically making
like creating a obligation upon yourself in a religious context. And by
the way, nobody says even with the ר"ש Rash that you can
create a נדר neder to do something not religiously related, right? So
it's still the irony of on the one hand מושבע ועומד מהר
סיני mushba ve'omed meHar Sinai says religious obligation it's harder to create
obligations, but on the other hand we have the only context of
a נדר neder is like to be נודר noder to God, וידר
יעקב נדר לאמור, vayiidar Yaakov neder lemor, right? So I can't be
נודר noder to mow my lawn tomorrow, I created an obligation on
myself, it's to be נודר noder to God. So you're נודר noder
to God something that is a religious sort of act, it's not
technically required because you want to give this צדקה tzedakah you want
to learn this פרק, but it's a religious act and you can
create this as a as a personal specific religious responsibility based after
the way the ר"ש Rash understands it through the model of נדר
neder of צדקה, tzedakah, creating a צדקה tzedakah obligation. And again, is
it דאורייתא, de'oraita, דרבנן, derabbanan, not clear from the ר"ש, Rash, but
it is a real responsibility and then we have to work within
the concepts of מושבע ועומד because you can't it's only in that
in that sort of space where you're not explicitly obligated to do
exactly this. Yes, Charlie?
But does it work in the opposite direction for
instance I am
I'm trying to become observant and I'm having trouble resisting the temptation
to eat non-kosher cheeseburgers? Right. And I make a נדר neder on
cheeseburgers.
Right. So, you know, easily you could just just make an make
that's easier then you just say all cheeseburgers are קונם konam or
cheeseburgers עלי, alai, right? It does seem that this is very much
קדשי שמים, kodshei shamayim, you know, to create this sort of obligation.
It's you know, we're in some צדקה... tzedakah... an interesting question whether
we can use this form in the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. What
would one naturally be the standard נדר? neder? The what? One more
question and then also one more
thing and then we have to move on. Yes. some oath a
few
days
ago, you know, about it sort of being the exact opposite of
יפתח Yiftach with not necessarily a נדר neder but with a you
know, he said something to the... משינה נורא. mishe'eina nora. Right, right,
that's true, that's interesting. Okay. So the other thing that I will
say also is about, you know, this גמרא Gemara that if somebody
does a דבר מצוה dvar mitzvah like a, you know, something דבר
טוב dvar tov three times it's like, you know, it's כאילו קיבל
על עצמו בנדר. ke'ilu kibel al atzmo beneder. What do you mean
קיבל על עצמו בנדר? kibel al atzmo beneder? Again, what type of
נדר neder, obligation to do something, you know? So that also points
to, you know, that idea where people say this idea like when
you do התרת נדרים, hatarat nedarim, חובותינו chovoteinu etc. לא מצד שבועה
ולא מצד נדר lo mitzad shevuah velo mitzad neder etc. So again,
that assumes a similar idea that you can create through your commitment
or through your words or maybe even sometimes through your actions implicitly
some personal religious obligation, right? So that it is a very important
category that ultimately is rooted in the in the in the פסוקים.
psukim. Okay, so now we'll continue. אמר אהא דאמרה. Amar aha de'amrah.
Okay. האומר לחברו, ha'omer lechavero, somebody says to his friend, נסק וניעול
לבי תרמודי. neissak v'niul l'bei Tarmodei. Hey, Michael, let's get up and
go to the Tarmodei. So, עלה הוא וחשטין. alah hu v'chashtein. You,
whether your friend listens to you or not, you the guy who
said this, you have to go up and do it early. א',
Aleph, so we may say let's, you created an at least obligated
yourself to cannot obligate somebody else to something. And it also seems
to be that the point is that you have to make sure
that you like beat him there, that you're there even earlier than
he is. שנאמר ויאמר אלי קום צא, Shene'emar vayiomer elai kum tzei,
God says קום צא. kum tzei. Get up, go out to the
valley, and there I will speak with you. ויצא אל הבקעה והנה
שם כבוד ה' עמד—and Vayetzei el habik'ah v'hinei sham k'vod Hashem omeid
השם Hashem was already there waiting for me. Okay, like a גמרא
Gemara story. אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. We go back
to חלום, Chalom, back to נידוי. Niddui. Okay, so that was a
very important digression there about the idea of נידוי. Niddui. מצוה, now
it's back to חרם. Cheirem. Wait, isn't נידוי Niddui even simpler than
חרם? Cheirem? Right. נידוי בחלום, Niddui b'chalom, if somebody had a dream
and they saw that somebody was putting them in חרם Cheirem in
a dream, צריכה עשרה בני אדם להתירה. tzrichah asarah b'nei adam l'hatirah.
So you have to, so the fact is that that might be
a symbol, that might signify that God has put you in חרם.
Cheirem. The תורה has, the גמרא Gemara has in other places this
idea like when בני ישראל B'nei Yisrael were in the מדבר, Midbar,
they were in חרם Cheirem from God.
Interesting question in general when people are put in חרם, Cheirem, is
it just a form of social control and they didn't like you
or are they seen as sort of agents of God, a way
of expressing divine displeasure and so on? Generally, a question when בית
דין Beis Din operate, do they, are they seen as operating as
an extension of God's punishment? Anyway, there certainly is a concept of
God putting people in חרם. Cheirem. So therefore in the
גמרא, yeah, נידוי Niddui and חרם Cheirem are used interchangeably, often נידוי
Niddui being more specific here. Anyway, so therefore, a person has to
be concerned that he's being put in נידוי Niddui from up, from
God. כדנידין מן המקום, K'denidin min haMakom, right, is a line in
the גמרא, right? So anyway, okay, so this idea of being נידויי
לשמים niduya l'Shamayim that came up a lot in מסכת תענית Masechet
Taanit if you remember, when it's not raining for a long time,
people have to feel like God has shown His displeasure and they
have to act כדנידין מן המקום, k'denidin min haMakom, like they're נידוי
Niddui from Heaven. So a person who has this dream, he has
to be concerned that he's being put in נידוי Niddui from Heaven.
So he needs ten people להתירא. l'hatirah. Now how can ten people
do it? Because as the ראשונים Rishonim say, because we say that
with ten people there is שכינה שרויה. Shechinah sheruyah. So if God's
presence is amongst ten people, then they can therefore act to represent
God and to release the person from the נידוי. Niddui. Even though
it was other people though, right? Isn't it just other people?
Right, I mean, there's the ר"ן Ran who raises that question, like
until you do this you have to act בדרך נידוי bederech Niddui
or not, and he doesn't know exactly what the answer is, but
it doesn't sound like it. Okay. So then the גמרא says והוא
דתני הלכתא, v'hu d'tani hilchata, that's only if they've actually learned, like
הלכתא Hilchata which means like
הלכות halachos
which means like not just משנה Mishnah but actually some תלמודיק Talmudic
learning. אבל מסני ולא תני, Aval masni v'lo tani, but now it's
funny because מסני masni means teach, if they taught but they didn't
learn, you'd think teaching is better, but it's right, if they taught
משנה Mishnah but they never learned גמרא, what? Some have the opposite
version, תני ולא מתני, tani v'lo masni, so they learned but haven't
taught, and it means the same thing. Anyway,
ואי לית דתני הלכתא, v'ei leis d'tani hilchata,
if you don't find ten people like that, ניזיל וניתבי אפרשת דרכים,
neizil v'nisvei a'parashat drachim, go sit by the crossroads where there's a
lot of people, maybe intersection,
ויהיב שלום לבי עשרה, v'yahiv shalom l'bei asarah, and keep on saying
שלום עליכם Shalom aleichem to people, עד דמלו עשרה ad d'malo asarah
דגמרי הלכתא, d'gamri hilchata, until you can collect, I think you can
get together ten people that have learned הלכות. halachos. Some say this
means you give שלום עליכם Shalom aleichem to everybody until finally ten
people who learned הלכות halachos say שלום עליכם Shalom aleichem to you
and that somehow counts as them מתיר matir your חרם. Cheirem. But
the other way of reading this is that the most ראשונים Rishonim
incline to, is that if ten people say to you שלום עליכם,
Shalom aleichem, that provides you some type of a protection from divine
punishment until you're able to convene a בית דין Beis Din or
whatever this special בית דין Beis Din that you need that will
really release you from it. אמר ליה רב אחא לרב אשי, Amar
lei Rav Acha l'Rav Ashi, so רב אחא Rav Acha said to
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ידע מאן שמתיה—מאן דשרי ליה?
So
if you know who put you in חרם, Cheirem, so can that
person release you from it? What?
In the dream, exactly. Right, in
the dream? So basically, you had a dream that somebody you knew
put you in חרם, Cheirem, put you in נידוי. Niddui. Can you
go to that person in real life and get him to release
you from it? Okay. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said
back to him, no, דלמא שליחא הוא דשדרוהו. dilma shlicha hu d'shadruhu.
Who knows? Maybe up in Heaven the dream signifies what's happening up
in Heaven, they assigned him as the agent to put you into
חרם Cheirem and into נידוי. Niddui. דלמא שליחא הוא דשדרוהו משמיה דשמיא.
Dilma shlicha hu d'shadruhu mishmeih d'Shamaya. He wasn't acting on his own,
if you saw him in a dream he was acting on divine
orders. So therefore you go to him in real life, he can't
release you, he's only authorized maybe by Heaven to put you into
נידוי, Niddui, not to release you from נידוי. Niddui. אמר ליה רב
אחא לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Acha l'Rav Ashi, so רב אחא
Rav Acha said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, שמתיה ושריה בהדיה בחלמיה
מאי? shamtiah v'sharyah behadeih b'chalmeih mai? Okay, how about if in the
dream itself, the same person that put you in נידוי Niddui released
you from the נידוי Niddui in the dream itself? It seems like
the dream cancels itself. So אמר ליה רב פפא לרב אשי, amar
lei Rav Papa l'Rav Ashi, Rav Papa said to Rav Ashi, okay,
how about if in between itself, the same person that put you
in נידוי nidui and released you from the נידוי nidui in between
itself, so it seems like the dream canceled itself out? So אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said to him, כשם שאי אפשר לבר בלא
תבן, keshem she-ee efshar l'bar belo teven, the same way it's impossible
for grain to not exist without there to be some straw, כך
אי אפשר לחלום בלא דברים בטלים. kach ee efshar lachalom belo devarim
betelim. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, כשם שאי
אפשר לבר בלא תבן, keshem she-ee efshar l'bar belo teven, the same
way it's impossible for grain to not exist without there to be
some straw, כך אי אפשר לחלום בלא דברים בטלים. kach ee efshar
lachalom belo devarim betelim. You can't have a dream without some nonsense
in it, like not all dreams are prophecy. So maybe you have
to be חושש choshesh that the part of you being פטור patur
from חרם cherem was the real part, and the part of you
being released was the not real part, so you still have to
be חושש. choshesh. It's amazing, right? I don't know. Moving on. Moving
on. I know. So there's a lot of different
למדן'ס lamdan's who take this, this one takes it more seriously, that
is correct. Okay.
רבינא הוה ליה נדרא לדביתהו. Ravina hava lei nidra l'devitehu. Now רבינא,
Ravina, his wife had a
נדר neder that she had made on herself, it was a type
of a נדר neder that it was either too late to annul
or wasn't the type of a נדר neder that a husband can
annul. אתא לקמיה דרב אשי, ata l'kamei d'Rav Ashi, he came to
רב אשי. Rav Ashi. אמר ליה, amar lei, בעל מהו שיעשה שליח
לחרטת אשתו? Ba'al mahu she'ye'aseh shaliach l'charatat ishto? Can a husband represent
his wife in the act of חרטה, charata, meaning the whole process
of releasing from נדר neder, is saying, had I thought about this
ahead of time I never would have done it. So let's say
his wife basically tells him, like he's not making it up, she
tells, explains to him the circumstances, and therefore he represents her in
front of the בית דין, Beis Din, can he do that in
order to release her from the נדר? neder, So אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said, אי מכנפין אין,
אי לאו לאו. ee michnafim in, ee lav lav. If you already
have a בית דין Beis Din gathered, yes, if not, no. Now
what does that have to do with anything? Let's read the conclusion
and then I'll tell you two ways of reading this גמרא. שמעת
מינה תלת, shamat mina telat, you can infer from this three things.
שמעת מינה בעל נעשה שליח לחרטת אשתו, shamat mina ba'al na'aseh shaliach
l'charatat ishto, the husband can represent his wife, ושמעת מינה לא שרי
למישרי נדרא באתרא דרביה, u-shamat mina lo sharei l'mishrei nidra b'atra d'rabeih,
you
should not, or
it's not appropriate somehow, to annul a נדר neder, in the presence
of your רבי, Rebbi, because why did he have to actually go
to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, why didn't he do it himself? Of
course it was his own wife, so we'll get back to that.
ושמעת מינה, u-shamat mina, you also can infer, כי מכנפין שפיר דמי,
ki michnafim shapir dami, if they're already gathered, it's good. Now there's
a lot of questions about this. Okay, first of all, the question
is what do you mean that you can learn that you're not
allowed to do it in the place of your רבי? Rebbi? We
learn, we learned in, a man is not allowed to annul the
vows of his wife, so it has nothing to do with the
place of his רבי. Rebbi. So some say okay, but why didn't
he just convene his own בית דין, Beis Din, get some other
people to come to him, why did he go to his רבי
Rebbi and you know, and ask his רבי Rebbi to sort of
take care of it? So that shows this idea of deferring to
the authority of the רבי, Rebbi, the idea of doing התרת נדרים
Hatarat Nedarim is an act of assuming rabbinic authority and so on.
But most significantly is this question of a בעל ba'al representing his
wife. So there's an important debate in ראשונים. Rishonim. The רמב"ם Rambam
thinks that this is only a husband representing his wife, it is
not anybody representing anyone else based on the principle of like אשתו
כגופו, ishto k'gufo, but the fundamental rule is that every person has
to appear him or herself directly in front of the בית דין.
Beis Din. This is only a very specific exception about the husband
and the wife. Okay,
and the issue about if they're already gathered is because this itself
is already such an exception that we allow a husband to represent
a wife, we don't want it to get out of hand, so
therefore we're only going to allow it under cases where they're already
at hand, we're not going to go make a big to-do about
gathering a בית דין, Beis Din, you know, in a case where
like it's already somewhat of a בדיעבד bedi'eved and something we're a
little bit uncomfortable with anyway. That's the way the רמב"ם Rambam understands
it. תוספות Tosafot disagrees. תוספות Tosafot says, no, no, no, he says
normally you can totally represent somebody else, because actually תוספות Tosafot is
also dealing with the case, it's clear that תוספות Tosafot does a
whole discussion, can you actually send a letter to בית דין, Beis
Din, can בית דין Beis Din annul a vow not in your
presence, like we're dealing with real cases where it's not פשוט pashut
that a person can always make it to בית דין. Beis Din.
And תוספות Tosafot has a general rule, you don't have to appear
in person in בית דין. Beis Din. The question was that if
you're representing your wife, you have a vested interest because you know,
you want to be free from the נדר, neder, right? So therefore
you might come, you might sort of give reasons that are not
like, oh yes, I'm sure she never would have meant it in
those circumstances, right, you'll sort of, even not consciously, you'll come to
make arguments that aren't really factual, in order to, you know, aren't
really correct, in order to get the התרה. hatara. And that's why
he says it's only if they're already gathered, because if they're not
gathered and you're going to go to all this effort to get
a בית דין Beis Din together and so on, it shows how
invested you are in getting the התרה, hatara, and therefore we'll say
in the case of husband and wife that we're not going to
be accurately representing the other party. So תוספות Tosafot uses this as
a unique problem because of husband and wife, but as a general
rule, and it seems like this was an important פסק psak for
תוספות, Tosafot, he says that people are allowed to send letters to
בית דין, Beis Din, they're allowed to use other ways, you know,
not in their presence. Yes.
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
I said maybe you weren't here, that it was a type of
a נדר that he was not able to annul. You only annul
certain types of נדרים, nedarim, נדרי עינוי נפש, nedrei inui nefesh, that
are things that imply, impact the marriage, and also ביום שמעו, b'yom
sham'o, it was after twenty-four hours, he can't annul it. Now the
other object switch which he gives instead of נדר and says that
it was הוה ליה נידוי. hava lei nidui. And therefore that solves
all the problems about how he could have done it himself and
why we're thinking he can't do it for his wife if it
wasn't a classic נדר situation, but that's not our גירסא. girsa. Okay,
let's just keep on going, the גמרא says like this: okay, now
the גמרא continues, ושמתא, v'shamta, if it's a case of נידוי, nidui,
אפילו באתריה דרביה, afilu b'asrei d'rabbai, even if it's your rabbi's location,
you can release somebody from a נידוי. nidui. Now that's fascinating, because
I would have thought that, you know, the problem of doing something
in the rabbi's location is that you're assuming a position of authority
when you're, right you know, when your rabbi's around. You should not
be like you're usurping your rabbi, you know, authority like you know,
you don't act as the big shot when your rabbi's around. So
I would think that releasing somebody from a חרם cherem is more
of an act of wielding authority than releasing somebody from a נדר,
because releasing somebody from a, right, חרם cherem is like we are,
we represent, you know, sort of rabbinic authority, you have violated, you
have done something, right, you know, that we're censuring and now we're
sort of accepting you back into the community, right, it's more public,
it's more representing the whole community, it's more representing Torah and standards,
it's not like a local personal question of is this vow binding
in this particular case. So that's what, what, תוספות Tosafot is גודר,
goder, right. So תוספות Tosafot says that, תוספות Tosafot says, תוספות Tosafot
says like this, yeah if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot
ושמתא, v'shamta, the first wide line here in the תוספות Tosafot under
the ר"ן, Ran, שמתא אפילו באתריה דרביה שפיר דמי להתירו השמתא דפעמים
שלא יהא רב מזומן shamta afilu b'asrei d'rabbai shapir dami lehatir hashamta
d'pe'amim shelo yehei rav mzuman sometimes the rabbi isn't around, או לאו
פנוי ואין לעכב היתר השמתא דעבד לגבי נדרים חשיב כהאי ליכא עכוב
היתר דיחיד נדר עליו עד שיהא רב מזומן להתירו, o lav panuy
v'ein l'akev heter hashamta d'avad l'gabai nedarim chashiv kahai leika ikuv heter
d'yachid neder alav ad sheyehei rav mzuman l'hatiro, you accept it upon
yourself, also it's not so onerous, אבל שמתא אין להשהות על האדם,
aval shamta ein l'hash'ot al ha'adam, it's not fair to leave this
person in this space. So that's interesting. Now on the one hand
there is the כבוד הרב, kavod harav, but you know, sort of
like the גמרא says, right, not exactly the same, but by analogy
it says, you know, it says, it says, אין חכמה ואין תבונה
ואין עצה נגד ה', ein chochma v'ein tevuna v'ein etza neged Hashem,
במקום שיש חילול השם אין חולקין כבוד לרב. b'makom sheyesh chilul Hashem
ein cholkin kavod l'rav. So here too כבוד שמים kavod shamayim is
like כבוד אדם, kavod adam, but yes it's, taking this role is
a פגיעה pgia in the כבוד הרב kavod harav but the person
in front of you demands that you actually go ahead and act
on this right now. Okay, so that is a very powerful statement,
ושמתא אפילו באתריה
דרביה, v'shamta afilu b'asrei d'rabbai,
you can do it even in your rabbi's place even though like
I said, it's in a way more of an assumption of authority
but there's a greater need, ויחיד מומחה שרי שמתא, v'yachid mumche sharei
shamta, and even an individual who is an expert even without a
בית דין beit din can release somebody from חרם. cherem. Okay, now
we'll take a look at what some of this, אמר רבי שמעון
בן זביד כי אמר רבי יצחק בר טבלא אמר רבי חייא אריכא
דבי רבי אחא אמר רבי זירא אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי חנינא
אמר רבי מיאשא משמיה דרבי יהודה בר אלעאי,
amar Rabbi Shimon ben Zavid ki amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Tavla amar
Rabbi Chiya Aricha d'bei Rabbi Acha amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rabbi Elazar
amar Rabbi Chanina
amar Rabbi Mayasha mishmei d'Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai, going to finish the
whole דף with that. מאי דכתיב, mai de'chtiv, what's meant by the
פסוק pasuk וזרחה לכם יראי שמי שמש צדקה ומרפא, v'zarcha lachem yirei
shmi shemesh tzdaka u'marpe, to those who fear my name, בני אדם
שהן יראין להוציא שם שמים לבטלה, bnei adam shehen yere'in l'hotzi shem
shamayim l'vatala, circling back to the over-liberal use of God's name. So
if you fear God's name, you don't just, you know, you're not
מוציא לבטלה, motzi l'vatala, and that's also a very appropriate like מוסר
mussar for people who make שבועות shvuot too much. Okay, but again,
it's the power of words and being very careful. שמש צדקה ומרפא,
shemesh tzdaka u'marpe, that's the end of that פסוק, pasuk, the sun
of righteousness heals. אמר אביי שמע מינה חרגא דיומא מסי, amar Abaye
shma mina charga d'yoma masi, that the חרגא דיומא, charga d'yoma, the
מפרשים mefarshim say the ר"ן Ran and the תוספות, Tosafot, it means
like, you know, sometimes you see those little dust mites in the
sunlight, you know what I'm talking about? Those little specks? So that's
what they say חרגא דיומא charga d'yoma means, that the sun brings
healing to it. So they just read the simple sense of the
פסוק, pasuk, that the sun brings healing. I don't know how they
get the word צדקה. tzdaka. ופליגא דרבי שמעון בן לקיש, u'pleiga d'Rabbi
Shimon ben Lakish, who should always learn שמעון בן לקיש, Shimon ben
Lakish, דאמר de'amar who says, he takes this פסוק pasuk very literally
about this world and he says, ואמר אין גיהנום לעולם הבא, v'amar
ein gehenom l'olam haba, there's no גיהנום gehenom in the world to
come. אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא מוציא חמה מנרתיקה, ela hakadosh baruch hu
motzi chama m'nartika, at the end of days God will, what will
God do to bring judgment on the world? He'll take the sun
out from its, you know, it's like a cloth, from its like
a, what's it called, נרתיק, nartik, sheath, skin, צדיקים מתרפאין בה ורשעים
נידונין בה, tzadikim mitrap'in bah u'rshaim nidonin bah, and the righteous people
will be healed by it and the wicked people will be burned
by it. שנאמר וזרחה לכם יראי שמי שמש צדקה ומרפא. shene'emar v'zarcha
lachem yirei shmi shemesh tzdaka u'marpe. So that פסוק pasuk is talking
about עולם הבא. olam haba. ולא עוד אלא שמתענגין בה, v'lo od
ela shemitangin bah, not only will the righteous be healed but they'll
be, they'll derive pleasure from it, שנאמר ויצאתם ופשתם כעגלי מרבק, shene'emar
v'yatzatem u'fishtem k'eglei marbek, you'll go out like these cows, והרשעים נידונין
בה, v'harshaim nidonin bah, the wicked... It's all going to be the
same, everybody's going to be in ישיבה Yeshiva the whole day. So
for the צדיקים Tzadikim it's going to be עולם הבא, Olam Haba,
and for the רשעים Resha'im it's going to be גיהנום, Gehinnom, right?
Well, that's like the other joke that they say because stories, it's
like the guy gets to go down to, he gets a tour
of גיהנום Gehinnom
and he goes down and like everybody's got this huge feast in
front of them, right, but their arms are, they can't bend their
arms, right, so they can't eat. So they're like, you know, in
agony. And then he goes up to Heaven and he sees exactly
the same thing, this huge feast and they can't bend their arms,
but everybody is feeding everybody else. Aha, okay. Alright, so, but the,
but this issue, this last point here about יחיד מומחה, yachid mumche,
there's a really important הלכתי halachic discussion about whether that applies, you
know, here where there's נדוי, niddui, what about שמשא, Shamsha, you know,
how does that apply to the issue about what defines מומחה? mumche?
Do you need like מסורה, masora, you know, do you need סמיכה
smicha going back to משה, Moshe, is that what we mean by
מומחה? mumche? You know, does the same discussion apply by נדר, does
it apply to to to שמשא? Shamsha? Let me just read you
one line here from the ט"ז Taz first. And it says like
this: ושמשא אפילו בד, v'Shamsha afilu bat, no, not that one. Where
is it? Hold on. Yeah, here it is: ושמשא אפילו בדאביד יחיד
מומחה שיש שם, v'Shamsha afilu de'avid yachid mumche she-yesh sham, 69 from
the bottom. הני מילי מהאי עידנא כלל לא ראי דאמר יעלו משמי
דאשר רבו כמדבשמשא שרי. Hani milei me-hai idna klal lo ra-id de-amar
ya'alu mishmi d'Asher Rabo ke-me-d'v-Shamsha sharei. Okay, by שמשא Shamsha again. והאי
יחיד מומחה דשרי שמשא, Ve-hai yachid mumche desharei Shamsha, this individual who's
an expert to release from the... איכא מן דאמר דוקא סמוך, ikka
man de-amar davka samuch, סמיכה כגון דמשה. smicha k'gon d'Moshe. ולא ניהו,
כל שהוא חכם...
כל שהוא חכם והוא בקי
בהלכות נדויין... Ve-lo nihu, kol she-hu chacham... kol she-hu
chacham ve-hu baki be-hilchos nidduyin... נדויין, nidduyin, we're talking about נדוי, niddui,
אף על פי שאינו סמוך הרי זה שרי נדרא. af al pi
she-eino samuch harazei sharei nidra. So first he's saying by a נדר,
נדר, it can be a יחיד yachid who's a בקי בהלכות נדרים.
baki be-hilchos nedarim. So that's the שמשא, Shamsha, ושמשא v'Shamsha in by
שמשא... Shamsha... לגבי התרת נדרים לא כתיב פרשת אלהים... le-gabe hataras nedarim
lo k'siv parshas elohim... סמיכין... smichin... תוספות Tosafos etc. So there's this
whole question, right, number one, does סמוך samuch here mean סמיכה כגון
דמשה רבינו? smicha k'gon d'Moshe Rabbeinu? And is the requirement by נדרים
nedarim different than the requirement by נדוי niddui and חרם? cherem? Because
although they're distinct, we've been talking about them in parallel, so that
remains the issue of some discussion. Okay, as I was saying...